And then trick number three is called
tools. And of course this is this is a
really exciting one and it really took
off in a massive way last year and and a
bit the year before as well. tools is
about realizing that when we have LLMs
generate tokens, the most likely output,
we could use those tokens not just to
generate just a a text response, but
also to decide whether or not the LLM
would like to carry out some actions
that it's been told it could do. So in
the prompt in in the input that you send
the LLM, you can say, "Hey, I'd like you
to answer my question, but by the way,
you can also respond with some special
tokens to say, I would like to search
the internet or I would like to use a
calculator or I would like to run some
Python code and then tell me what." And
if you respond with that, then I will do
that action for you and then I will call
you a second time with the results. And
that little clever trick which is called
using tools, it allows us to use an LLM
not just to generate a text output but
actually to decide to do something. We
call it running a tool and then we will
run the tool and provide it back with
the response. But you always have to
stay grounded in the reality that the
LLM itself isn't going off and searching
the internet or running Python code. An
LLM is just a statistical engine that
generates tokens, but we are
interpreting those tokens. It's
generating tokens that says something
like, I would like to run a calculator.
And we're interpreting that output and
we're running the calculator. So, it's
always our code. It's always software
that ends up calling a tool. We're using
the LLM just to generate the tokens to
say what it wants to do next. And that
whole process is called tools. and it's
really clever. All right, I just want to
make this super real for you just just
to be very clear. Here is something
hopefully familiar to you. This is chat
GPT and I'm going to paste in a question
I have for it. Okay, before the question
I I want to I want to prefix it. to use
Python code to respond to the next
question. Just reply Python colon and
then a Python expression here. And then
my question, what is the square root of
pi? A question which perhaps isn't going
to be very easy for a language model to
respond to, but I'm telling it that it
can do something special. It can reply
this way if it wants to just execute
Python code. So, I'm going to run that
and we'll see how it responds. And this
is how it responds. Uh, and you can see
that it's uh it's done something it's
done something reasonably advanced
because it's doing it all in one line,
including imports, which which I assume
will work. But it's it's actually
decided instead of responding with the
square root of pi, it's responding with
this Python line of code right here.
Quite a clever Python line of code. And
and so you can see that that that
basically it's it's using a tool. We've
equipped chat GBT with this tool that
we've just used language for. And when
we've asked it this question, it hasn't
given us the answer. It hasn't just told
us the square root of pi, but rather
it's said that it wants to execute some
Python code. And this is like a super
clear example of what it means to have
an LLM use a tool. It's just about
giving it a clever input and then
interpreting the output. That is what
tool calling is all about. And the
fourth trick is something that's so
simple. It's super elegant. It's
basically saying what could be better
than calling an LLM with an input and
getting some output. Or what could be
better is calling it multiple times. In
fact, in a loop, we can we can call an
LLM and then when it's when it's uh
produced its output, we can ask it if
it's finished yet, and if not, we just
call it again and then again and then
again in just a loop, repeating until a
goal is met. And that simple idea of
calling an LLM multiple times is
something which turns out to allow us to
achieve much bigger goals than just
calling an LLM once with an input and
getting an output. And so that fourth
trick of the loop is something which
allowed us to achieve much bigger
things. So those are four tricks. There
are lots of other tricks, but these are
the big four tricks that allow us to get
from the sort of beginnings from the
chat GPT of of 2022 to some of the high
performance products today like cursor
agent and claude code. Okay, now it's
time for me to define an AI agent for
you. So, uh, there's been a lot of
different definitions of AI agents. And
in fact, there was a meme a while back
that that an AI agent could be whatever
you wanted it to be because it was so
hyped and because everyone meant
something a bit different. There there
have been a few different definitions
that people have really sort of stood
behind over the years. And one of the
earliest ones came from OpenAI and and
others that described it as AI systems
that can do work for you independently.
This is the idea behind products like
GPT agent that used to be called
operator. Uh and this was something
where where this is something where
where you can prompt it and it will like
open up a browser and you can watch it
while it goes off and searches the web.
It looks for restaurants that have
availability this evening for the
particular type of food you like with
with reservations for four and it will
make the reservation while you watch and
you have that sense that there is
something there that's working
autonomously and that is the sense of
having an AI agent that is doing work.
Some other people use a similar
definition that it's something that can
act as well as generating tokens. it is
an LLM that can act. Uh, which you know
it's it's it's uh it's it's hard to to
be super crisp about what that means,
but you kind of know it when you see it.
And that was the first of the
definitions of an AI agent. And then the
next one came in I guess early 2025 and
I think it was Hugging Face first of all
the the the New Yorker AI startup that
described it as AI systems where an LLM
controls the workflow. An LLM controls
the workflow. So an LLM as it's
generating output tokens those tokens
describe what should happen next and
orchestrate future LLM calls. that that
became the definition and Anthropic kind
of double down on that with a with a
seminal blog post called building
effective agents that had a similar
definition and that for a long time was
like the prevailing definition of an AI
agent but more recently the definition
that's really taken hold that's become
the definition that I think Simon Willis
who I'm who I mentioned before was
perhaps the the first to to really sort
of plant the flag and say this is going
to be the definition. It came in in late
2025 and it is that an an agent is where
there is an LLM that runs tools in a
loop to achieve a goal. It runs tools in
a loop to achieve a goal. So it ties
back to a couple of those those uh uh
tricks that I just mentioned tools and
loop. So it's something again it runs
tools in a loop to achieve a goal. And
I'm hoping that already clicks for you.
But if not, remember what we did
yesterday with the cursor agent when we
gave it a goal. We said, "I want a first
person shooter in a web page." And off
it went. We'd given it a goal. It was
obviously in a loop because we saw stuff
happening one after another. We saw
files being created. It was an LLM being
repeatedly called again and again. And
it had tools. It had tools to write
files to disk. It had tools to run code.
It had tools to generate code. So it had
these various tools and it was using
those tools and you could see it
happening. And so that gave you like a
firstirhand experience of an AI agent.
It was running tools in a loop and we
gave it a goal and it achieved it. So
that is the current winning definition
of an AI agent.